Guide to the Philip Butcher Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Philip Butcher Papers,
1864-2005
[Bulk Dates: 1940-1990].
Butcher, Philip, 1918-
6.75 linear ft. (14 document boxes, 1 flat box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0176
4079733
The Philip Butcher Papers contain correspondence, journals, subject files, research files, printed material, and photographs related to the life and work of Philip Butcher, primarily, but also related to James Butcher. Philip and James Butcher, brothers, were professors at Morgan State University and Howard University, respectively.
Biographical Note
Charles Philip Butcher (1918- ), born and raised in Washington, D. C., graduated from the prestigious Dunbar High School. His mother, Jennie Rosa Lawrence Jones Butcher, like her mother before her, was a teacher. James W. Butcher (1875-1950), his father, retired in 1926 from a job with the Government Printing Office and became a wood-worker. He was best known for the "Butcher-Built Dollhouses" that he crafted and sold to fine department stores from Washington, DC to New York City.
Philip Butcher, who specialized in American Literature, received an AB (1942) and an MA (1947) from Howard University, and in 1956 he was awarded a doctorate from Columbia University. From 1947 until his retirement, Butcher taught in the English Department of Morgan State University in Baltimore, Maryland. He became a full professor in 1959, the same year that his first book, George W. Cable: the Northhampton Years, was published by Columbia University Press. Cable had been of interest to Butcher since his student days at Howard University and had been the topic of his Master's thesis. Butcher was married to Ruth Butcher with whom he had two daughters, Wendy and Laurel.
World War II temporarily interrupted Butcher's scholarly trajectory and he served three years (1943-1946) in the United States Army. Although Butcher spent most of the war in Great Britain as an NCO in the Special Service Division, he did a stint at Fort Huachuca, Arizona, where the 92nd and 93rd Infantry--two entirely African-American Divisions--were trained. After V-E Day he was transferred from Britain to Germany with the 449th Signal Heavy Construction Battalion. Butcher, was discharged with the rank of Technical Sergeant.
Actor-playwright-director and Howard University professor James W. Butcher (1909-1994) was Philip's older brother. James received his undergraduate degree from the University of Illinois in 1932 and his Master's degree, in theatre, from the University of Iowa in 1941. During World War II, James, who achieved the rank of 2nd Lieutenant, served as a Theatre Consultant with the Special Service Division of the United States Army, which had been established to provide recreation and entertainment for the troops. His initial posting was Fort Huachuca, Arizona, but in 1943 James was assigned to Liberia. When a German submarine sank the merchant vessel, Cape Decision, in which James was traveling, he and the other survivors drifted around the Atlantic on a life-raft for ten days before being rescued. His second attempt to reach Liberia was successful and James spent over two years, writing and directing theatre productions, along with Ossie Davis, in Monrovia.
James taught at Howard University from 1934 to 1976, excluding his stints in the US Army or pursuing graduate education. For the last thirty years of his life he was married to Vada Easter Butcher, his third wife. He had one daughter, Grace Toni Jones, from his first marriage to Grace Desmond. Margaret Just Wormley was his second wife.
Philip and James Butcher had three sisters: Edith Harris, Nellie Forsyth (1904-1989) and Jennie Weir.
Scope and Content
These papers consist of correspondence, journals, photographs, printed material, ephemera, clippings, programs and playbills related to the professional careers and World War II service of Philip Butcher and his brother, James.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series
Series I. Correspondence, 1940-1997
Series II: Subject Files, 1864-2005, Undated
Series III. Research Files, 1883-1997
Series IV. Personal, 1930-1989, Undated
Subjects
Howard University Players.; Butcher, James W., Jr.; Butcher, Philip, 1918-; Butcher, Vada E; Cable, George Washington, 1844-1925.; McPherson, James Alan, 1943-; World War, 1939-1945--Liberia.; World War, 1939-1945--United States--Personal narratives, American.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
10/06/86 M-86-10-06 Papers Butcher, Philip Gift
11/16/89 M-89-11-16 Papers Butcher, Philip Gift
12/26/90 M-90-12-26 Papers Butcher, Philip Gift
08/17/92 M-92-08-17 Papers Butcher, Philip Gift
Gift of Philip Butcher, 1986, 1990 & 1992.
Selected Related Material-- at Other Repositories
James W. Butcher Papers, Moorland-Spingarn Research Center of Howard University.
James W. Butcher Papers, 1910-1949 (MS 507) Historical Society of Washington, D. C.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1940-1997
  The ingoing and outgoing correspondence in this series relates primarily to Philip Butcher's academic career. Correspondents, many of whom were Butchers' mentors, colleagues and students, include Arna Bontemps, Lionel Trilling, and James Alan McPherson among others. Writing projects, conference proposals, research queries and other academic interests are the topics of most letters. A few brief manuscripts can be found within the correspondence.
  - Catalogued Correspondence--Arna Bontemps, 1948-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Catalogued Correspondence--Braithwaite-West, 1940-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Edgar Creek, 1943-1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Thomas Cripps, 1970-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ralph Ellison, 1954-1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Shelley Fisher Fishkin, 1985-1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - David Levering Lewis, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - James Alan McPherson, 1971-1984, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - William Rhoden, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Roy Simmonds, 1984-1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Publishing Correspondence, 1948-1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence, 1943-1989, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 12 to 13)
- Series II. Subject Files, 1864-2005, undated
  Included here is an array of material, both personal and professional. Clippings, bulletins, conference proceedings, committee work, funding applications, photographs, and autographed articles written by Philip Butcher's former students and colleagues at Morgan State University are here. Also included are programs, playbills, and photographs of James Butcher's professional activities at Howard University. A smattering of correspondence can be found within the subject files.
  - Afro-American Literature, 1928-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - William H. Beardsley, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Arna Bontemps, 1943-1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - William S. Braithwaite, 1928-1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Sterling Brown, 1947-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sterling Brown--Phonograph Record, Undated (Box 14)
  - James Butcher
    - Biographical Info, 1942-1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Howard University Players, 1937, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Howard University and Spelman College--Video Tapes and Film, 1965-1966, 1981, 1996, Undated (Box 16)
    - Howard University--Norway Theatre Workshop, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Professorial Career, 1949-1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Plays, 1948-1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Playbills and Programs, 1935-1983 (2 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Production Photos, circa 1920s-1960s, 1980s (2 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 4 to 5)
    - General, 1949-1999, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - James Butcher Sr., 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Margaret Just Butcher, 1947-1957, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Vada Butcher, 1978-1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Center for Editions of American Authors, 1967-1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Clippings--General, 1951-1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - College Language Association, 1956-1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Thomas Cripps, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Ossie Davis, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Deans of Black Grad Schools, 1975-1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Frederick Douglass, 1967-1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ralph Ellison, 1942-1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Walter Fisher, 1977-1988 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Stephen Foreman, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - David Harris, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Highlander Folk School, 1953-1961 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Lincoln Bible, 1864-1933 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    (information regarding)
  - Lincoln and Sheridan Letters, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    (copies)
  - London, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - MELUS, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Kelly Miller Pamphlets, 1900-1917 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Modern Language Association, 1974-1982
    - Hubbell Award Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Nominating Committee, 1974-1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Nominating Committee, 1976 (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 3 to 4)
  - Morgan State University, 1953-1978
    - Faculty Pamphlets, 1953-1978 (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 5 to 6)
    - General, 1958-1961 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Lucy Moten Fellowship, 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Negro Writers Conference, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The Octoroon, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Permissions--Ethnic Image in Modern America, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Printed Materials--Interracial Understanding, 1918-1981 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Printed Materials--General, 1923-1987 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Research--Louisiana, 1948-1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Research--The Race Problem, 1918-1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - R.S. Simmonds, 1985-1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Southern Negro Youth Conference Bulletin--Autographed, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Students, Former--Published Articles, 1986, Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Arlin Turner, 1948-1978 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Darwin Turner, 1958-1976 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Mark Twain, 1935-1991 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - University of Iowa--Robert Corrigan, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Carl Waltz, 1958-1966 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - World Literature Today, 1973-1985 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Richard Wright, 1941-1968 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Series III. Research Files, 1883-1997
  William Stanley Braithwaite, George Washington Cable and Thomas Walker--three of Butcher's longstanding research interests--are the primary focus of this series. Materials include notes, clippings, correspondence, photographs and ephemera related to his research.
  - William Stanley Braithwaite
    - Correspondence--Edward Starr, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence--Research, 1964-1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence--Library, 1964-1971 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence--Permissions, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Research Files, 1938-1981 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - George Washington Cable--Correspondence
    - Publishing, 1958-1974 (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 6 to 7)
    - Anna Gertrude Brewster, 1943-1972 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Brewster Diary, 1893-1897 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Alma Edwards, 1949-1967 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Adelene Moffat and Family, 1896-1997, (5 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 4 to 8)
    - Adelene Moffat--Portrait, circa 1900 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Letters to the Editor, 1965-1981 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Research Inquiries, 1947-1963 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Research Inquiries, 1944-1964 (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 1 to 2)
    - College Libraries, 1948-1969 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Public Libraries, 1959-1971 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - George Washington Cable--Research
    - Cable Family, 1945-1968 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Williams and Franklin, 1946-1949 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Notes, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - General, 1884-1967 (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 8 to 9)
    - General, 1902-1978 (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Northampton, 1908-1960 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Northampton Correspondence, 1949-1962 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Cable Speech, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Cable Publications, 1941-1971 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Walker Family
    - Thomas Walker Correspondence, 1895-1932 (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 7 to 8)
    - Thomas Walker Photo, 1951, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Walker Receipts, 1885-1899 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Annie Walker, 1948-1992 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Fannette Walker Penn, 1906-1924 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Walker Ephemera, Undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Walker Photographs, Undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Walker Memorials, 1935-1936 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Frederick Douglass, 1891-1945 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - General Research, 1883-1995 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Other Subjects
    - Mark Twain and Warner Thornton McGuinn
      - Correspondence, 1963-1969 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Research, 1912-1968 (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Twain Article Controversy, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Sterling Brown, 1940-1969 (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 11 to 12)
    - General Research
      - Articles, 1947-1973 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Books--Annotated, 1885, 1927, 1950-1969, (3 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 2 to 4)
      - Books, 1941, 1956 (Box 16)
      - "George Washington Cable: Early Realist of Negro Life"--Dissertation, M.A., 1947 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Series IV. Personal and Professional, 1930-1989, Undated
  The bulk of this series concerns Philip and James Butcher's service in the US Army during World War II. A typescript copy of Philip's extensive World War II journal is here. The material created or gathered by James Butcher includes a journal, notes and photographs of a trip from Monrovia to Dunbar Farms in the interior of Liberia; and a lifeboat log kept by H. E. Sorenson, Master of merchant vessel Cape Decision, which was torpedoed early in 1943 enroute from Charleston, SC to Dakar. James was on the Cape Decision, when it was hit and spent ten days, journeying 900 miles to safety, with Sorenson. This series also contains US Army service handbooks and bulletins, Fort Huachuca publications and ephemera related to the variety of entertainment provided by the Special Services Division.
  Also included here are a few of Philip Butcher's projects and proposals.
  - Clippings, 1930-1989 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1970, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - World War II
    - James Butcher
      - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Diary and Lifeboat Log, 1943, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Liberia--Notes and Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Liberia--Photos, 1943-1944 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Philip Butcher
      - Journals and Notes, 1945-1946 (3 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 6 to 8)
      - Office of War Information--Radio Proposal, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Printed Material, 1942-1949, 1960 (1 of 2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Printed Material, 1942-1949, 1960 (2 of 2 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Printed Material--Clippings, 1937-1944 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Writings and Projects
    - “Freedom’s People”--Scripts, 1941-1942 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Lectures Undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Phylon, 1948-1949 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Proposals, 1948-1970, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Society for the Study of Southern Literature, 1967-1976 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      (includes Louis D. Rubin correspondence)
      - Television Script--The Negro in U.S. History, 1974-1975 (Box 13, Folder 7)